Guide to the Katharine Brush Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Katharine Brush papers
1942-1956
YCAL MSS 463
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.92
(7 boxes)
The Katharine Brush papers consist chiefly of material relating to an unpublished novel by Brush entitled "Lover Come Back". The novel, started in the early 1940s, went through multiple revisions and had a working title of "Story of Sylvia". Materials relating to the work include research files, outlines and synopses, drafts, and supplementary material, such as excerpts, discards, and schedules. The papers also include research files on military topics.
Brush, Katharine, 1902-1952
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Thomas S. Brush, 1956.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Katharine Brush (1902-1952)
Katharine Brush (1902–1952), the author of short stories, novels, articles, and screenplays, was born Katharine Ingham, in Middletown, Connecticut, to Charles Samuel and Clara Louis Ingham, and raised in South Byfield, Massachusetts. Brush began writing fiction in 1923 and won recognition with the novels Young Man of Manhattan (1930) and Red-Headed Woman (1931). Other works include a short story collection, Night Club (1929), and a semi-autobiographical novel, This Is on Me (1940). She married twice, in 1920 to Thomas Stewart Brush, the owner of a chain of newspapers in Ohio, and in 1929 to Hubert Charles Winan.
Biographical information taken from New York Times (1923-Current file); Jun 11, 1952; ProQuest Historical Newspapers The New York Times (1851-2007), pg. 29 (accessed 9 May 2011).
Scope and Contents
The Katharine Brush papers consist chiefly of material relating to an unpublished novel by Brush entitled "Lover Come Back". The novel, started in the early 1940s, went through multiple revisions and had the working title "Story of Sylvia". Materials relating to the work include research files, outlines and synopses, drafts, and supplementary material, such as excerpts, discards, and schedules. The papers also include research files on military topics.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Series I. Writings, 1942-1956. Series II. Research Material, 1943-1951.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors; Brush, Katharine, 1902-1952
- Writings, 1942-1956; Series I; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Writings contains extensive material relating to an unpublished novel by Brush with the initial working title "Story of Sylvia," changed later to "Lover Come Back." The novel, started in the early 1940s, went through multiple revisions, and includes corrections and comments from editors. Materials relating to the work include research files, outlines and synopses, drafts, and supplementary material, such as excerpts, discards, and schedules.
  - Donor list and description, 1956 (Box 1)
  - [Story of Sylvia], research files, 1943-1951; 3 (Box 1)
  - [Story of Sylvia], draft, "first version", 1945 (Box 1)
  - [Story of Sylvia], draft, "second version", 1946 (Box 1)
  - [Story of Sylvia], draft, "3rd put-together", 1947 (Box 1)
  - [Story of Sylvia], draft, "Doubleday's cuts of the 1947 put-together", 1947 December (Box 2)
  - "Story of Sylvia," draft, "4th put-together [or] semi-final version", 1948 (Box 2)
  - "Story of Sylvia," draft, 1948 "cut-down version", 4 (Box 2)
  - [Story of Sylvia], "Pre-1950 outlines, synopses, memos, correspondence...", 1949-1950 (Box 3)
  - [Story of Sylvia], drafts, "3rd copy", 1950; 14 (Box 3)
  - [Story of Sylvia], drafts, "3rd copy", 1950; 14 (Box 4)
  - [Story of Sylvia], drafts, "3rd copy", 1950; 4 (Box 5)
  - [Story of Sylvia], "Outlines and suggestions as of 1950...", 1950-1951 (Box 5)
  - [Story of Sylvia], "List of third copies sent to Chappaqua", 1951 March (Box 5)
  - [Story of Sylvia], draft, "Parts I & II of the Barbara-Larry story-line...", 1951 (Box 5)
  - "Story of Sylvia," draft, "YBG copy", 1951; 2 (Box 6)
  - [Lover Come Back], "August 1951 ... rough run-thru" (Box 6)
  - "Lover Come Back," draft, 1952 March; 2 (Box 6)
  - "Lover Come Back. Miscel. bits collected in 1954", 1950-1954, undated (Box 7)
  - [Lover Come Back], "Wartime and dated excerpts from discards book...", undated (Box 7)
  - [Lover Come Back], "The supplementary pages", 1950-1952, undated (Box 7)
  - [Lover Come Back], "Alternate idea for the 2nd triangular flashback...", 1951 October (Box 7)
  - [Lover Come Back], "Follow-up via Sylvia...", 1951 November 12 (Box 7)
  - [Lover Come Back], "Sample chapter outlines", undated (Box 7)
  - [Lover Come Back], "Time schedule for book", 1942, 1951 (Box 7)
  - [Lover Come Back], "Statistical sheets for various characters of the book", undated (Box 7)
  - [Lover Come Back], "A few rough draft pages", 1955, undated (Box 7)
  - [Lover Come Back], "Not yet filed", undated (Box 7)
  - [Lover Come Back], untitled, 1952, undated (Box 7)
- Research Material, 1943-1951; Series II; 3
  Arranged alphabetically by folder heading.
  Series II. Research Material contains research files on topics relating to the U.S. military.
  - "Infantry training", 1943-1944, undated (Box 7)
  - "Lt. Col. John C. Meyer", 1944-1951, undated (Box 7)
  - Untitled, 1944-1951, undated (Box 7)